Guide to the Martha J. Lamb Papers 1756-1892 (Bulk 1876-1892) MS 362
New-York Historical Society
Martha J. Lamb papers
1756-1892 (Bulk 1876-1892)
New-York Historical Society
MS 362
7.5 Linear feet (18 boxes, 3 oversize folders)
The Martha J. Lamb Papers contain a variety of material relating mostly to Lamb's professional life as historian, author, and editor. Much of this collection pertains to Lamb's tenure as editor of the Magazine of American History (1883-1893) including submissions, letters from readers and contributors, and correspondence dealing with internal production matters. The collection also contains letters received by Lamb regarding her work as an historian and author, a journal (1878-1879), and material for a number of Lamb's articles and addresses, including clippings, reviews, drafts, notes, correspondence, and proofs, and drafts of her History of the City of New York. Material in this collection also relates to activities of the Huguenot Society of America, various historical societies, scientific organizations, trade groups, social clubs, and the charitable societies of the Madison Square Presbyterian Church. In addition, the papers contain poetry, notes, financial and genealogical material, ephemera, visual material, and artifacts.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Arrangement
The Martha J. Lamb Papers are organized in the nineteen series listed below. Within each series, arrangment varies, but is usually alphabetical or chronological. See series descriptions in the container list for details.
A small amount of material is housed in oversize cabinets, marked as "Ov" on container list. The call phrase for these items is "Y-Lamb."
Series I.
Magazine of American History, 1883-1893, undated
Series II.
Lamb, Correspondence, 1769-1892 (bulk 1876-1892), undated
Series III.
Lamb, Journal, 1878 Oct. 18-1879 Apr. 21
Series IV.
Lamb, Articles and Addresses, 1874-1890, undated
Series V.
History of the City of New York, drafts, undated
Series VI.
Clippings, 1756-1892 (bulk 1876-1883), undated
Series VII.
Huguenot Society of America, 1879-1892, undated
Series VIII.
Madison Square Presbyterian Church, 1882-1889, undated
Series IX.
Organizational Material, 1854-1892, undated
Series X.
Poetry, 1869-1883, undated
Series XI.
Notes, undated
Series XII.
Financial Material, 1882-1891
Series XIII.
Genealogical Material, 1891-1892, undated
Series XIV.
Ephemera, 1873-1890, undated
Series XV.
Excursion: Marietta, Ohio, 1888
Series XVI.
Copies of Documents, undated
Series XVII.
Huntington Collection catalog, 1883
Series XVIII.
Visual Materials, [18]81, 1886, undated
Series XIX.
Artifacts, 1881, undated
Biographical chronology
Dates in the life and career of Martha J. Lamb
1826/29 Aug. 13 Born Martha Joanna Reade Nash, Plainfield, Massachusetts, 1826 according to her sister and tombstone; 1829 according to newspapers, early biographic dictionary entries, and Library of Congress Name Authority File.
1847 First publication, "A Visit to My Mother's Birthplace" in the Hampshire Gazette.
1852 Marries Charles A. Lamb, mechanic, furniture salesman.
1857 The Lambs move to Chicago; Lamb becomes involved in charitable work including the Home for the Friendless, the Ladies Industrial School Association, and the 1863 Sanitary Fair.
1866 or early 1867 Lamb moves alone to New York City, apparently leaving her husband. In New York, she begins to write fiction, children's books and to conduct historical research. Lamb becomes active in charitable work in the Madison Square Presbyterian Church and in numerous societies.
1876–1881 Her History of the City of New York: Its Origin, Rise and Progress is sold in parts by subscription, then published in two volumes.
1878 Nov. 5: Lamb is first woman to address The New-York Historical Society, lecturing on Lion Gardiner and Gardiner's Island.
1883 Lamb forms the Historical Publication Co. in order to purchase the Magazine of American History. She takes over as editor, a position retained until her death, with the May 1883 issue.
1893 Jan. 2: Dies of pneumonia in New York City.
Lamb's New York City addresses
1866 or 1867–1873 29 E. 24th St.
1873–1893 Coleman House, 27th and Broadway
New York City addresses of the Magazine of American History Magazine of American History
18??–1887 30 Lafayette Place
1887–1893 743 Broadway
Related Material at The New-York Historical Society
• Madison Square Presbyterian Church societies' papers, 1882 (1 volume). Includes the constitution of the Loan Relief Society. Most of this material is in Lamb's handwriting or is addressed to her. Call phrase: BV NYC Churches Presbyterian.
• Misc. Lamb correspondence (5 items) in various collections. See card catalog.
• Magazine of American History letterbooks, 1877–1881 (6 volumes), before Lamb's tenure as editor. Call phrase: BV Stevens, John Austin.
• Library collections contain Magazine of American History, 1877–1893 with index. Also several of Lamb's publications including History of the City of New York: Its Origin, Rise and Progress.
Scope and Contents
The Martha J. Lamb Papers contain a variety of material relating mostly to Lamb's professional life as historian, author, and editor. The bulk date from 1876 through 1892. Much of this collection pertains to Lamb's tenure as editor of the Magazine of American History (1883-1893) including submissions, letters from readers and contributors, and correspondence dealing with internal production matters. The collection also contains letters received by Lamb regarding her work as a historian and author of the History of the City of New York, and a journal of Lamb's (1878-1879) detailing her workdays. Material for a number of Lamb's articles and addresses, including drafts, notes, correspondence, and proofs, illustrate her research, writing, and publication processes, as do drafts of her History of the City of New York. Twenty-seven scrapbooks kept by Lamb include clippings of her published articles and reviews of her work, documenting her career from 1863-1883.
Martha Lamb's prodigious involvement in numerous organizations is reflected in this collection. Material relates to activities of the Huguenot Society of America, where Lamb served as chairman of the Ladies Committee, various historical societies, scientific organizations, trade groups, and social clubs. The collection also includes items pertaining to Lamb's charity work in New York, conducted through the Madison Square Presbyterian Church led by the reformer Rev. Charles Parkhurst.
In addition, the Martha J. Lamb Papers contain poetry, notes, financial material (bills and receipts), genealogical material, and ephemera, including advertisements, tickets, invitations, and calling cards. A small amount of material relates to an 1888 excursion to Marietta, Ohio. Miscellaneous items in Lamb's possession include a collection of mostly late eighteenth century letters, copies of historical diaries and letters, and a Metropolitan Museum catalog. This collection also contains a few photographs (including cabinet cards of Lamb), prints, sketches, watercolors, tintypes, glass negatives, and printing blocks, many of which relate to her historical work. Assorted artifacts include a small cache of rocks, a sprig of heather, and a key.
The collection contains little personal material of Lamb's—a few items can be found among her correspondence, financial material, ephemera, and artifacts. In addition, Lamb's diary contains some personal information, though it deals mostly with her professional life as a writer and historian. The great bulk of the correspondence in this collection is letters received, with only a few copies and drafts of Lamb's letters and responses.
Martha J. Lamb, in her capacity as historian, published author, and magazine editor, effectively represents a public Victorian woman. This collection of mostly professional papers supports research in the history of nineteenth century women editors, writers, journalists, and historians. Although much of the material does not delineate the complexities faced by Lamb as a career woman, she does occasionally divulge her strategies. In an 1884 letter to Esther Herrman, for example, Lamb writes: "I am quite sure that you fully understand why I deem it the wiser course to do my work in the quietest possible way. Mine is a notable field, and if I provoke any opposition, there are plenty of aspiring men who would take the opportunity to get astride my pathway—thus making obstacles all the harder to overcome. My hope is to so triumph in the end that all womenkind will be benefitted [sic]."
This collection, with its abundance of Magazine of American History material, also broadly supports research in American historiography, and the histories of publishing and journalism. In addition, articles, notes and ephemera pertaining to New York City can be found in Lamb's papers.
Note: Lamb used a number of pennames, most of which were derived from family names. The names "Nash Vinton" and "Vinton Reade" appear in this collection. She also used the names "Nash Reade," "Emogene," and, probably, "Crisp."
Separated Materials
• Magazine of American History letterbooks, April 4, 1884–1892 (7 volumes) Call phrase: BV Magazine of American History.
• Forty genealogies transferred to the Library in 1957, families unknown.
Advertisements.; Announcements; Articles; Cabinet photographs.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Diaries.; Drafts (documents); Ephemera.; Genealogies (histories); Invitations.; Invoices.; Minute books.; Notes (documents); Poems; Printing blocks; Prints (visual works).; Proofs; Receipts (financial records); Reports.; Scrapbooks.; Sketches.; Tintypes (prints); Tickets.; Visiting cards; New York (N.Y.) -- History.; United States -- Historiography.; United States -- History.; Associations, institutions, etc. -- United States.; Charities -- New York (State) -- New York.; History -- Periodicals.; Magazine of American History; Periodicals -- Publishing.; Women authors, American -- 19th century; Women journalists -- United States.; Women periodical editors -- United States.; Women publishers -- United States.; Lamb, Martha J. (Martha Joanna), 1829-1893 -- History of the City of New York; Lamb family; Reed family; Huguenot Society of America; Madison Square Presbyterian Church (New York, N.Y.)
- Series I. Magazine of American History, 1883-1893, undated
  - Subseries 1. Submissions, 1883-1892, undated
    Scope and Contents note
    Articles, "Minor Topics," documents, prints. Bulk is articles. Arranged alphabetically by contributor. Letters and envelopes that accompanied these submissions remain with them. Many have Lamb's editorial comments added (usually on envelope). Further correspondence regarding submissions (follow ups, corrections, etc.) are filed in Subseries 2. Contributors include Frederick Law Olmsted on parks and landscape gardening, historian William Leete Stone, and postmaster-general Horatio King.
    - Submissions, A - B, 1889-1892, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Submissions, Ca - Ch, 1891-1892, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Submissions, Cowley, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Submissions, Co - D, 1885-1892, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Submissions, Este, Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Submissions, F - G, 1883-1891, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Submissions, H, 1883-1891, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Submissions, J, 1885-1887, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Submissions, K, 1883-1885, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Submissions, L - M, 1885-1890, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Submissions, N - O, 1883-1889, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Submissions, P, 1886-1890, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Submissions, R, 1883-1889, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Submissions, S, 1883-1892, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Submissions, Stone, 1890, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Submissions, T - We, 1885-1892, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Submissions, Wh - Wo, 1883-1889, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Submissions, Unidentified, Undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Submissions, Unidentified, Undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Submissions, alienated envelopes, 1886-1892, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Subseries 2. Letters received from readers and contributors, 1883-1892, undated
    Arranged by sender. Includes letters regarding published articles (corrections, comments), magazine subscriptions and copies, queries, replies to queries, notes, and contributors' follow-up correspondence regarding their submissions.
    - Letters received, A, 1886-1892 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Letters received, B, 1883-1892 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Letters received, C, 1883-1892 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Letters received, D, 1883-1892, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Letters received, E - G, 1883-1892, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Letters received, H - I, 1884-1892, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Letters received, J - K, 1883-1892, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Letters received, L - M, 1884-1892, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Letters received, N - P, 1883-1892, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Letters received, R, 1883-1892, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Letters received, S, 1883-1892 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Letters received, T - V, 1888-1892, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Letters received, W, 1887-1892 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Letters received, Unidentified, 1883-1892, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Alienated envelopes, 1885-1892, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Subseries 3. Letters received, re: MAH production matters, 1884-1892, undated
    Arranged by sender. Includes letters from publishing trade associates regarding printing, engraving, advertising in MAH, and journal exchange. Also letters from employment seekers and advertisements/ circulars sent to MAH.
    - Letters received, re: printing, engraving, advertising, employment, 1884-1892, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Letters received, re: journal exchange. Also advertisements/ circulars, portrait catalog, 1892, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Subseries 4. Letters sent (copies/drafts), 1883-1891, undated
    Includes a small number of copies and drafts of Lamb's responses to the above letters. For further copies of responses, see the seven letterbooks for the Magazine of American History in the Manuscript Department (call phrase: BV Magazine of American History). These letterbooks cover April 4, 1884 -- Dec. 1892. Each volume contains an index.
    - Letters sent, copies/drafts; also empty envelopes, MAH, 1883-1891, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Subseries 5. Notes and clippings, 1886, 1892, undated
    Includes notes and newspaper clippings about various historical societies' events for the magazine's "Societies" section, advertising, and a few of Lamb's drafts of notes and queries for publication.
    - Notes and clippings re: societies, 1892, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Lamb re: MAH advertising, notes and queries, 1886, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Series II. Lamb, Correspondence, 1769-1892, undated (bulk 1876-1892)
  Letters received arranged by sender; copies and drafts of letters sent arranged chronologically. Most correspondence in this series pertains to Lamb's work as historian and writer, although there are a few personal items. Two small collections of correspondence between others sent to Lamb are also included in this series.
  - Subseries 1. Letters received from publishers, 1876-1890
    Letters from Lamb's publishers, A.S. Barnes & Co. and University Press/ John Wilson & Son, regarding History of the City of New York.
    - Letters received, A.S. Barnes & Co., 1876-1890 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Letters received, A.S. Barnes & Co., re: subscriptions for History of the City of New York, vol. 2, 1880 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Letters received, University Press/ John Wilson & Son, 1876-1880 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 2. Letters received, 1871-1892, undated
    - Letters received, A - B, 1877-1892, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Letters received, C - D, 1871-1892, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Letters received, J. Watts DePeyster, 1877-1886, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Letters received, E - H, 1878-1885, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Letters received, I - M, 1878-1892, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Letters received, N - V, 1878-1892, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Letters received, W, 1878-1889, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Letters received, unidentified (also alienated envelopes), 1877-1881, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Subseries 3. Letters sent, 1871-1886, undated
    - Lamb, copies and drafts of letters sent, 1871-1886, undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Subseries 4. Letters, collections, 1769-1880, undated
    One collection consists of letters, mostly to John Reade, 1790-1804, from various senders including Richard Harison, Walter Livingston, and George Ludlow. This John Reade does not appear to be related to the Reades in Lamb's family. Lamb refers to the collection as "autographs." Sent to her by John W. Hamersley, 1880 (his note included). Another small collection, letters between R.M. Hartley and John A. Bryan, pertains to the New York Juvenile Asylum.
    - Letters between R.M. Hartley and John A. Bryan, 1861, sent to Lamb, 1861, undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Collection of letters, mostly to John Reade, 1790-1804, 1769-1828, 1880, undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
- Series III. Lamb, Journal, 1878-1879
  Lamb's title is "Memorandas and Notes of great interest—Preserve." Entries concern Lamb's articles and the History of the City of New York, lectures (including a lengthy description of her Nov. 5, 1878 address before The New-York Historical Society), social engagements and callers, correspondence, illnesses, Madison Square Presbyterian Church attendance, and sewing. Housed with scrapbook volumes in Box 10.
  - Journal, Oct. 18, 1878-April 21, 1879 (Box 10)
- Series IV. Lamb, Articles and Addresses, 1874-1890, undated
  Drafts, notes, correspondence relating to, and proofs of a few of Lamb's articles and addresses. Arranged alphabetically by title. Publication information follows title if known. One folder is housed in the Manuscript Department's oversize cabinets (Ov); call phrase: Y-Lamb, folder *1.
  - "Amasa J. Parker": correspondence (MAH Sept. 1890), 1889-1890, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - "American Life Saving Service": proofs (Harper's Feb. 1882), Undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - "An American Museum. The New York Historical Society Building," Andrews' American Queen, 1879 Feb. (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - "Chief Justice Morrison Remick Waite": drafts, notes, correspondence (MAH July 1888), 1888, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - "Electioneering in 1701. Exciting Political Controversies of Colonial New York," Brooklyn Daily Eagle, 1885 Nov. 1 (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - "Historic Mansions of New York": notes (mostly blank), 1882 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - "Historical 'Claremont'," Mail and Express, New York, 1885 Aug. 21 (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - "In the Yale Library," New Haven Palladium, 1882 Jul. 31 (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - "Less Known Incidents in the History of New York", Undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - "Lion Gardiner, Founder of the Manor of Gardiner's Island": copy of address read before N-YHS Nov. 5, 1878; see also "Manor of Gardiner's Island," (MAH Jan. 1885), Undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
    Scope and Contents
    With newspaper accounts of Lamb reading the paper before the New Haven Historical Society, 1882. Also contains a long New York Times piece, "Lion Gardiner's Island," dated August 10, 1879 and signed "E.A.D.," which is probably by Lamb.
  - "Lyme, a Chapter of American Genealogy": notes, correspondence, 1874-1885, undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - "Lyme, a Chapter of American Genealogy": drafts, Undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - "Manor of Shelter Island": draft, notes, correspondence, photograph (MAH Nov. 1887), 1884-1887, undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - "New York": draft (promotional essay for History of the City of New York), Undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - "New York Biography": notes, correspondence, 1878, undated (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - "New York Biography": drafts, Undated (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - "New York City in 1789," Once a Week, undated (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - "New York One Hundred Years Ago," Harper's Weekly supplement, 1876 Feb. 19 (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - "Newark": notes and drafts, Undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - "Nicolas Bayard": draft (MAH ), Undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - "Old-Time Politics. A New York Conflict at the Beginning of the Last Century," Philadelphia Press, 1885 Nov. 1 (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - "The Silk Industry of America—Corticelli Sewing-Silk," Andrews' American Queen, 1880 Jul. 17 (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - "Sixty Waymarks in the World's Progress": proofs, notes (MAH Aug. 1890 as "Vinton Reade"), Undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - "State and Society in Washington," Harper's New Monthly Magazine, 1878 Mar. (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - "A Terrible Time. Election Scenes of 1701 in Colonial New York," Sunday Times-Star, Cincinnati, 1885 Nov. 1 (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - "Van Renssalear Manor": copy of address before Long Island Historical Society, Dec. 26, 1882 (revised and published in MAH Jan. 1884), Undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Draft of speech before a gathering of women of the press in Boston (Possibly New England Women's Press Association, founded 1885), Undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - "Christmas Owl": proofs, 1881 (Box Ov, Folder *1)
- Series V. History of the City of New York, drafts, undated
  There are two drafts for a number of these time periods; some dates overlap with the rewriting. Also notes and documents for HCNY.
  - Table of Contents, Preface, Vol. 1, Undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Drafts, 1613-1664, Undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Drafts, 1664-1678, Undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Drafts, 1678-1689, Undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Drafts, 1689-1702, Undated (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Drafts, 1701-1720, Undated (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Table of Contents, Vol. 2; Drafts, 1710-1726, Undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Drafts, 1750-1775, Undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Drafts, 1775-1780, Undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Drafts, 1780-1800, Undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Drafts, 1800-1819, Undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Drafts, 1832-1868, Undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Notes and documents for HCNY, Undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Series VI. Clippings, 1756-1892, undated (bulk 1876-1883)
  Includes twenty-seven scrapbook volumes containing clippings of many of Lamb's published articles, reviews of History of the City of New York and other publications, articles about Lamb's activities, and items on various topics. Five folders of loose clippings include articles about Lamb, particularly reviews of HCNY. Also loose newspaper clippings on various topics, and articles from eighteenth century magazines.
  Scrapbooks are arranged roughly by content, then chronologically (dates overlap). The volumes have been numbered for paging purposes.
  Some of the published articles are signed, but a number are unsigned, or a penname is used (the name "Crisp" occurs frequently). As Lamb was known to use pennames, and these pieces appear in scrapbooks along with signed articles of Lamb's, she is assumed to be the author.
  - Clippings, newspaper re: Lamb, 1879-1887, undated (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, newspaper, 1879-1892, undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Clippings, newspaper, 1879-1892, undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Clippings, newspaper, 1879-1892, undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Clippings, magazine: Universal Magazine, Annual Register, Gentleman's Magazine, Nation, 1756-1796, 1891, undated (Box 9, Folder 10)